[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software Frances Perry is a tech
lead and manager for Google cloud
dataflow a unified batch and streaming
programming model she was previously a
developer on the flume project and
internal data processing infrastructure
and she is a co-author of the Google
data flow paper Francis welcome to
software engineering radio thank you
looking forward to chatting absolutely
so what is a stream ah so stream
processing is basically a style of data
processing where you're continually
processing data as it's coming in live
and you're producing live results
continuously a year ago I was doing
several shows about streaming frameworks
and streaming systems and I continually
asked the question what is the
difference between batch and streaming
and I think different people have
different answers to that question what
is your response to that question so I
think I want to take that even one step
further
I think that's the wrong question to be
asking so in the way we want we
encourage people to think about data
processing is that you're really when
you what you want to separate into the
shapes of your data and then how you
choose to execute it so in that sense
we're encouraging folks to use the terms
bounded and unbounded when they refer to
their data so that's talking about
whether if your data is bounded you have
it all right now you can just go grab
some file pattern off some file system
and there's the data that you want to
process if your data is unbounded it's
continually streaming in now given those
two things there are multiple ways in
which you could choose to execute that
data there's the traditional
style systems that everyone's familiar
with like hadoop mapreduce that style
and then there's the the more real-time
systems that people are familiar with
but I think I don't think of those as
two different axes I think of it as a
spectrum because there's actually a
really big continuum between sort of
processing all your data at once
processing it continually in small
records and then in the middle there's
the style that people call incremental
batch sometimes or micro batch streaming
where you're processing small subsets of
the data at a time sort of like a cron
job over little little batch jobs so
you're talking about this unbounded data
in streaming systems the data is often
unbounded it never stops coming from the
point of view of the server you're just
getting infinite data
how does handling unbounded data streams
differ from handling a finite data
stream so I think the thing that makes
it really tricky in the place where it
gets really fun is when we start looking
into the distinction between event time
and processing time so event time is the
time the data was actually generated
when when the event happened and
processing time is when it arrives in
the system for for processing now to
really understand that I think it's
really helpful to use an example I
didn't I didn't crack this myself till I
had a good concrete use case so let's
imagine we are building a mobile gaming
app or something right so we got users
on their mobile phones around the world
playing some sort of game doing some
sort of mind-numbing tasks over and over
again earning points right they're
crushing candy or slaying zombies or
something
now those users are earning points for
their team and we want to be able to
process that data and figure out what
the team scores are over time so if you
look at that when the user is processing
went playing the game and they they
crush the candy and they earn some
points that's the event time right the
time the time when the score happened
the processing time though is when that
arrives in our system so if they're
online and nothing's wrong wonky in the
network the data will actually arrive
for processing very quickly but there's
many reasons that that can slow down so
perhaps there's a bit of network
congestion or something and some of the
elements arrive out of order in our
system so we're getting some elements
from some users slightly delayed
and even more commonly in mobile
gaming's though we want these games to
be working in offline mode which means
that the users play in this game you
know in c-26 be on an airplane flight
and off in airplane mode and they land 8
hours later and that's when we get the
score so in this point our system is
processing data some of its fresh and
happening right now and some of it might
actually be 8 hours old and it's all
coming in at the same time and so that
distinction between when the data
happened and when it arrives make
streaming systems and real-time system
is quite complex the gaming example is
interesting because gaming is this you
can think of it as just a you know not a
serious application but it's it seems
paradigmatically similar to the types of
applications we might be building in the
future because there is such a large
influx of data would you say that's
accurate are our applications going to
become increasingly data intensive and
more quote unquote real-time absolutely
I think you know people have really
started to figure out what kinds of
insights you can gather from data and so
the data itself is people are gathering
more and more because they see how
valuable it can be and at the same time
we're doing so many more things in a
distributed fashion right when you're
you're not just dealing with a couple of
servers gathering data you've got people
on mobile devices and everything becomes
much more distributed and when you're
dealing with distributed systems you
have to be able to deal with the
uncertainties that come with that
so one uncertainty that you have been
talking about is event time skew can you
define that in more detail right so the
event time skew is is basically the
difference for an element in when it
happens and when it arrives in the
system and so when you're dealing with
with large amounts of data there's sort
of the the skew that you're generally
seeing and then some elements may be
even worse than that so I think another
way of putting it a venn time skew is
the difference between the processing
time and the actual event time would you
say that's accurate yes okay so how
significant of a problem is this event
time skew
I think it really depends on your
application so for many things you know
well for many situations you're
absolutely fine dealing with processing
time if that's enough for the algorithm
that you're trying to process your data
with in other cases if you're trying to
talk about events and in relation to the
other events that happened at the same
time event time skew is really going to
mess you up so let's say we are trying
to calculate the total score for one of
our teams in a particular hour right
we've calculated that result and if
we're doing a streaming system you know
presumably late low latency is important
to us we want to be able to get you
these results in near time near
real-time so maybe we've got a dashboard
and we're trying to show you know which
teams are currently at the top of the
ranking and if we go ahead and sum the
scores from 12:00 to 1:00 o'clock and we
give you that result and then 8 hours
later one of those team members lands on
their foot their flight lands they come
back online and we get more scores it's
now 8:00 p.m. and we need to figure out
how to go back and deal with the fact
that the data that we generated at 1:00
p.m. was wrong because we've got
additional updates that came in and we'd
like to refine that result ok I want to
spend more time talking about the event
time skew and how we deal with that but
I'd like to take a step back and talk a
little bit more about streaming systems
in general and historically particularly
for the listeners who are a little
unfamiliar with streaming systems so
streaming systems are sometimes
associated with this idea that you get
incomplete or approximate results
because there is this giant influx of
data why has has there historically been
a notion that streaming systems give
these incomplete or approximate answers
I think because it is so difficult to
deal with these late arriving elements
and to reason about them in a way that
makes sense
people have just kind of thrown up their
hands and said you know what we'll just
assume that when those late elements
come in after some threshold we'll we'll
just ignore them so I know that my
system is going to be slightly lossy but
it's still great to get low latency and
so that's a trade-off I'm willing to
make but we want people to start
thinking about though is that that that
trade-off isn't necessary with the right
abstraction
and and ways of reasoning about these
complex systems we can actually get both
correctness and still be able to handle
late arriving data and one of the
band-aids that people have used
sometimes is this lambda architecture
which uses batch to provide eventually
correct results that can complement that
streaming inconsistency why why has this
been a thing that people have used why
are people using batch to complement
their streaming inconsistency so I think
yeah when you're streaming runtime isn't
able to give you guaranteed correct
results what the trade-off you're often
willing to make is that every night I'll
run a batch job to get my correct
results and during the day because I'd
like just to see some something more
real-time I'll be ok with approximate
results and then basically I'll throw
those away at the end of the day and
rerun my batch program to get the
correct updates and so a system like
that
works but we think it can be unnecessary
right and it's also much more difficult
to manage because you're dealing you
have to manage both the streaming and a
batch system often you end up having to
write your computation in two different
ways with two different API it's and two
different sets of concepts and I think
that's unnecessary okay so why why is it
unnecessary why isn't the lambda
architecture good enough like how can we
roll this the functionality of both a
batch and a streaming system into one so
I think there what it comes down to is
when you have the right set of
abstractions and concepts for reasoning
about these types of programs you can
reason you can do both in one so it's it
there's just no need to do them
separately and so that's basically
what's at the root of what used to be
called the data flow model so the data
flow model is something that evolved out
of a lot of work internally at Google we
actually had a very similar set up to
the lambda architecture for awhile where
we had MapReduce obviously which we'd
used for many many years and we evolved
that into a system called flume which
basically put a higher-level
graph style API on top of Map Reduce to
make it much easier to program and then
separately we evolved some real-time
systems mill-wheel was our continuous
real-time processing system and what we
found is that so many teams inside
Google had both they had their MapReduce
job they were running nightly for those
correct results and then they were also
running a mill wheel system for more
real-time results but you know mill
wheel itself can actually do a really
good job of not losing data it started
to develop those right concepts that let
us realize that we could have actually
correct streaming results and when we
realized that we started to merge the
two systems and see see if we could you
know make it so that people didn't have
to do both they could do one system and
and then tune after they wrote their
algorithm what is the latency
requirement that I need in this
particular use case this interesting
that the lambda architecture was
essentially in place at Google at the
same time that people were talking about
it outside of Google like I think the
discussions around it originated from
Nathan Mart's who I don't think ever
worked at Google but I guess it's funny
how these things develop in parallel at
different places exactly I mean I think
engineers they they see the problem and
they all you know everyone was trying to
solve the same things you know
internally we did a huge amount to
innovate and how we did big data
processing but we were sort of heads
down and doing it in our very internal
homogeneous environment and obviously
the external community took you know the
MapReduce paper and a number of other
ideas and ran with that too and it's
great to see they ended up going in
similar directions so I think one way to
articulate why the lambda architecture
is probably not the best sustainable
solution is that it has this assumption
baked in that we can look at our data in
a periodic fashion we could just think
of these daily jobs that resolve our
data as an okay thing but one quote from
the dataflow paper that I think counters
this is we as a field must stop trying
to groom unbounded datasets into finite
pools of information that
ventually become complete and instead we
must live and breathe under the
assumption that we will never know if or
when we have seen all of our data can
you explain this quote in more detail
yes I think you know one of the things
we want people to start thinking about
is that even your traditional notion of
batch processing and bounded data is
actually often streaming data or
unbounded data so you know when you have
your log files and you're taking your
logs from Tuesday and running a nightly
cron job on them and then the logs from
Wednesday and you're running a nightly
cron job people think of that as you
know batch processing but really what
they've done is they've taken an
infinite stream of data and forced it
into these finite chunks they've
artificially sort of divided it into
finite pieces so that you can then
process it with a batch system and
there's actually a number of drawbacks
to that so for example if you're
processing you know you're dealing with
the latency of the batch system so if
you're trying to calculate the top users
per hour right you've got by 1:00 a.m.
you may have most of the data needed to
do that for that hour but if your
nightly batch job isn't gonna run till
midnight of that day you're waiting 23
unnecessary hours for that data another
issue is that by artificially putting in
these boundaries between the days to
separate your infinite unbounded data
into finite chunks you may lose the
ability to analyze certain portions of
your data so there's a concept called a
session which is a very common way that
people analyze web logs and so on and a
session basically gathers up a burst of
user activity so this is like if
somebody was playing our mobile game and
they were playing playing playing for
you know 20 minutes and then they went
to get a cup of coffee and chat with
someone and then they came back and
played for another few minutes we might
want to treat that as two different user
sessions or activities and usually when
you try to analyze those you're you're
separating them by the time the user was
offline between the activities but when
we force our data into these fixed
chunks we lose the ability to track
sessions that cross that boundary so for
example user starts playing our game at
11:55 to 1:00 a.m. we might lose the
fact that that was a single session if
we process it the
stays data completely separately from
the second day's data so the data flow
paper also talks about how the
programmer is always making trade-offs
between correctness and latency and cost
when you are programming against an
unbounded data flow could you explain
how these three desirable
characteristics are typically traded off
right so completeness is exactly that
notion of how to deal with late data so
if I want to give you the total score
for for the teams in this hour if I do
it right when that hour ends I'm a risk
completeness lack of completeness
because there might be late data that
comes in after that point so that's a
trade-off I can make if I want to be
completely sure that I have gotten all
the data for in that time period I could
wait maybe an hours enough maybe two
maybe a week right at some point you
start if there's you have to figure out
how long you want to wait to ensure
completeness and you can see how that
immediately counteracts latency because
the longer I'm waiting to get
completeness the longer I have to wait
for any sort of result and often that's
that's not what you want you want sort
of speculative results so far I know
there's this score and then you want to
evolve that result and refine it over
time as additional work comes in and
then of course both of those there's
going to be a cost aspect because the
more data you're buffering the more
often you're computing it you know the
more computing resources you need to put
behind that okay and so I want to come
back to talking about the the dealing
with the event time skew you talked
about sessions there's also this concept
of a windowing where windowing is the
concept of partitioning our data set
along temporal boundaries is sessioning
a version of windowing yes absolutely so
let me separate that into into two
pieces there's actually two again we we
always want to think about having these
two time dimensions right there's event
time and there's processing time
so the notion of windowing in the data
flow model divides your data up into
finite chunks of event time so you
there's multiple ways to do that fixed
windows are sort of the most common so
every hour's worth of data every minutes
worth of data and again this isn't when
the data arrives this is when the data
occurred and there's sliding windows so
every 24 every hour give me the last 24
hours worth of data and then sessions is
you know give me sort of bursts of user
activity the other dimension that you
might want to divide things up on is
processing time and there's a separate
notion called triggering that we use to
divide up the processing time okay as
we're talking about these different
windowing strategies these strike me as
things that were around even in the
streaming systems that acknowledged that
we were getting some inconsistencies
these streaming systems that were
complemented with batch in order to have
the lambda architecture how can we move
towards a conversation where we talk
about how windowing is used in order to
make our streaming systems have a higher
degree of correctness well I think
people have used the notion of windowing
for a very long time but what's been a
more recent shift is this distinction
between event time and processing time
so often when people used windowing in
the past they were sort of just
referring to what my data arrived some
more processing time based windows but
we've really seen a shift recently in
streaming systems towards recognizing
that this distinction is is important I
see can you give an example for how we
might use windowing to improve the
resolution of our data in that type of
gaming application right so I think in
that in that gaming application what you
need to do is figure out you know first
of all what are the kinds of results
that you'd like so there's multiple ways
we could choose to accumulate so there's
two basic types of processing that you
want to do the first and the style of
system is more element-wise processing
so that's something like filtering or
parsing or
normalizing data something that requires
you only to look at annex Ingle element
we're very used to that in Map Reduce
that's your your map function right
you're just taking individual elements
and processing them doing that in a
streaming system is pretty easy you just
need to be able to scale to handle the
data volumes and then you just apply
this function to each element as it goes
past
it's the aggregations that get more
complicated and this is where you're
looking at multiple elements at a time
so the count of all scores for this team
right you need to take all these
individual scores that have the same
team and and sum them together when
you're doing that these aggregations
this is where you need some notion of
dividing your data up so you can make
progress the question you know what is
the total score for this team over all
time doesn't make sense because you're
not gonna ever actually get to the point
where you have that result so when doing
is a way to let you start doing those
aggregations okay can we talk about
water marks and what water marks do for
our streaming systems absolutely so when
we get this goes back to that event time
skew right so when you are trying to
process data in fixed windows so I want
to process the data that happened in
every hour so I want all the data all
the scores that happen in between noon
and 1:00 o'clock and I'm gonna sum those
together now you immediately have to
decide when can I do that some right so
at 1 o'clock I could summit but I
probably won't have all the data if I'm
assuming my data can arrive out of order
so when do I know that it's good enough
should I go at 1:15 1:30 3 o'clock right
you have to pick that point when you
think you've seen all the data so the
watermark helps you track that
conceptually a perfect watermark would
let you know exactly when you've seen
all the data for a given time so you
know at this point you will see no more
data that happened between 12:00 and
1:00 o'clock
it's what the watermark would tell you
now a perfect watermark is very very
unlikely there are some systems that
could support it so for example if
you've got an append-only log file right
you you do know and your time stamping
elements based on when they get appended
into that log file you are able to read
those in order
but whatever you're dealing with a
distributed system you have to more
likely use a heuristic watermark which
is your the system's best guess of data
completeness so the system will sort of
track how data is flowing into the
system and give its best guess that yes
now I think I've seen all the data from
12:00 to 1:00 o'clock so maybe that
happens at 1:10 and at this point your
system says great I can go ahead and sum
those results and give you that that
output ok so a definition of a watermark
it might be that a watermark lets us
track how completely we have processed
our event data with respect to event
times so a watermark with a value of
time X indicates that all input data
with event times less than X have
already been observed exactly could you
talk a little more about what the
advantages of using watermarks are well
watermarks let's you very very carefully
track this distinction between event and
processing time right without it you
have to just make a call like I'm gonna
wait 2 hours and and then I will go
ahead and sum that that score for that
fixed window that I want and and
reproduce it and when you do that you
are not gonna be able to adapt if the
data becomes really late maybe there's a
fiber cut across the Atlantic and a
whole bunch of stuff slows down right
you'll still just go ahead and too
eagerly some stuff and send the result
down the pipe on the other hand you also
may have to be too conservative a lot of
the time and you're introducing this
unnecessary latency so it basically
forces you to without the watermark you
sort of have to pick a time where you're
gonna throw up your hands and just move
on what is a trigger so a trigger is
sort of the opposite of a window in that
it applies to processing time so right
now we've been talking there sometimes
when the event time isn't necessarily
what you want you just want to suss if
I'm just calculating a global score for
each team doesn't really matter to me
when the elements happened I can just
say every 10 minutes of processing time
take whatever data I've gotten and sum
it up and go ahead and emit that result
so triggering basically is that other
axis
and it can also interact with event time
because I might want to say I'm summing
scores every day I want to use the event
time and get a fixed window daily fixed
windows and so that would basically say
every 20 you know once I've seen all the
data for Tuesday and the watermark has
passed and I think I'm done getting data
for Tuesday I'm going to emit that
result but if I do that I've got very
low latency so I can also use a trigger
to say every hour I'd like an update of
how that sum for Tuesday is progressing
can you talk a little more about the the
architecture for how these events are
being placed from the client to the
server so for example is it like the
clients constantly streaming off events
from the game or from the uber
application or some other real-time
application with unbounded data and the
server is just aggregating all of these
events in a queue and deciding when to
process those events based on windowing
and or just give me a better picture of
how that architecture looks like and how
the server is determining where these
windows are being processed or where
these windows are being imposed upon
right so the watermark is actually a per
source concept so each input source
defines its own definition of a
watermark and how you can track what's
going on with that source so the system
will be asking each of the individual
sources about their watermark and then
using that to calculate a global system
watermark so we do want to try to
separate here very much what we call the
data flow or beam model concepts which
is generally how you want to describe
this data from the particular system
details at some point we should talk a
little bit more about Apache beam and
the distinction between that and data
flow and I can go into details on that
then absolutely we should we should talk
about that now so so we've been talking
about streaming in a somewhat general
context but what we are really talking
about is the data flow model of
streaming so can you explain how this
data flow model that we've been
discussing how does that contrast with
the other streaming models that
were prominent before dataflow right
well I think it comes down to the the
fact that the the data flow model is
what evolved out of this internal work
at Google that sort of took MapReduce
and then flume and mill-wheel and all
these systems and design this this one
that unified batch and streaming use
cases into a single model so this is
where we realize that if we can come up
with the right set of concepts for
letting you reason about this style of
programming you won't have to do it
differently for streaming and batch and
so the data flow model really focuses on
that on that unification and it works
based on four main questions so the
first one is you talk about what you're
computing what does the algorithm you're
doing are you doing joins histograms
counts sums that kind of thing the
second axis is where which is our
shorthand for where an event time what
do you want to do about the event time
of the data does it come from
fix windows hourly windows sliding
windows the next one is sorry what where
when when is in processing time so how
often do you want to trigger your
results and then finally how what do you
want to do when multiple results are
emitted for a window when we refine a
result over time should those accumulate
and how should those relate so what
we've really done is taken all these
concepts and put them into a very clear
framework that lets you really clearly
tune each of those concepts so you can
build your same data processing
algorithm that you want to do and then
by that's your what right the bulk of
what you're doing is is the what
question what am i trying to compute
over my data and then you tune the other
three questions to basically adapt that
algorithm that single algorithm from a
traditional batch style use where you've
got all your data you just want to
process it and get a single result out
into a more continuous real time data
data where you have to start tuning how
often and how complete you want your
results to be so with that said with the
data flow model defined what is a patchy
beam so this is a lot of fun right so we
took
we worked on data flow it came out you
know based on this internal evolution of
work we've been doing and we also
created the cloud dataflow Google Cloud
dataflow which is part of Google cloud
platform and it is a system for
executing these pipelines so you can
sort there's two separate concepts here
right there's the programming model
which is the the SDKs and the API is
that let you express your data
processing pipelines and then there's
the service for actually executing those
pipelines so you know what happened when
we designed this is that the model
itself is a key way to use the service
the model is what gives you these really
intuitive ways for writing these
pipelines the right you know tools for
reasoning about event and processing
time and it also has the right hooks so
that the system can very efficiently
execute these things but by designing a
new SDK and a new programming model you
really make it hard for users to adapt
and take over and start using a system
right because there's a huge barrier for
users to rewrite their programs to learn
these concepts and to invest in that so
what we realize is that this programming
model itself has has a huge amount of
value and if we contributed that to the
open source community we can let that
model grow and and flourish and at the
same time we could have a one of these
systems and the places to run that so
what we did is take that data flow model
basically and donate it to the Apache
Software Foundation so it's currently in
incubation as the incubating project
Apache beam and so beam is now what we
used to call sort of the data flow model
and what we're really excited about is
we're working with the community to
build different runtime options so you
can take this beam program and you can
run it on cloud dataflow but you can
also run it on other existing systems so
you can run beam pipelines on Apache
spark you can run them on a patchy flink
we've got some we've just had a gear
pump runner added we've got interest in
apex and storm and other systems so is
writing a program that is compliant with
the beam spec is that kind of like
writing a
program in one specific language that
can be put through an interpreter to a
variety of other languages and then the
the analogies to the language here would
be these different processing systems
like flank or SPARC exactly so you think
of it like you know what's in beam is
the description of your data so that's
where we use the terms bounded and
unbounded right you're talking about
purely the properties of your data and
how you'd like to process it so this is
this is your API for expressing that and
then when you're ready to run that you
choose sort of what you want to compile
it into do you want to you know have it
translated into spark concepts and
executed on spark do you want to
translate it into flink run it there or
so on so let's go through an example
with that game so if we were developing
a we wanted to to use the beam a model
on our game what kinds of abstractions
do we need to define across the events
of our game right so let's start with
answering the what question so the what
question we're just gonna do simple
score summing right so we'll take our
input data
well parse each element to extract the
team and the number of points scored for
that team and then we'll do a sum to get
the number of the total score per team
so that's our what that's the first
question right and we could just sort of
take that and run it in a traditional
batch style over some large amount of
input data but now if we want to evolve
that we can start answering those other
questions so we can answer the where the
windowing and we can take that same
algorithm that we wrote add one other
one or maybe two lines of code depending
on how long you like your lines and say
and now do this in fixed windows so
every hour give me a different sum so at
this point we're starting to take that
single algorithm and evolve it now we
can go further and we can say we can
adapt it into a streaming pipeline by
saying how often we want to trigger
those results so I'd like I'd like
hourly windows and I'd like to know how
those are progressing every 10 minutes
so every 10 minutes give me an update on
what my hour
the windows look like and why would it
be useful to run this model on storm
versus spark versus flank versus data
flow once we define it once we define
this unified programming model version
of our streaming feature of our
application why might we want to you
know how would these different
processing systems contrast in the way
that they would actually execute that
model all right well this picture this
really becomes down to user choice right
some some folks like to run on premise
some folks like to run in the cloud some
folks like to use open source some folks
want to be part of an integrated
platform so this is really where your
your choice comes up just you know the
more choice users have for where they're
processing their data the better things
are because they've got their data in
different places they've got different
requirements they wanted the freedom to
move between those systems and not be
locked in so is it just about the
lock-in or are there certain types of
operations that might run faster on
spark or might run faster on data flow
yeah absolutely so what I mean what
we're trying to do here is generalize
there's sort of two things right we want
to generalize how you reason about the
style of programming it so the most
intuitive model that we can so that's
that's the first step we drive the beam
model the you know based purely on what
makes sense for reasoning about the
style of programming then we want to
give you the portability of running that
model across multiple environments but
each of those environments is a little
bit different right every every one of
those systems has things that can and
cannot do as well as the others and so
that's where we work really hard to
categorize you know which features each
of those runtimes will be able to
support in the beam model what are the
streaming systems that do conform to the
beam model so the closest one right now
with the the cleanest alignment is
Apache flink so I think you know there's
there's definitely some information out
there that the Flint guys were really
excited to read the data flow model
paper and so they went off and they took
some of those concepts and they
integrated them deeply into flink
so it's notion things notion
of event time in processing time align
beautifully with with the beam model
systems like spark are sort of moving in
the right direction spark 2.0 has a lot
of new features that will really help
align those but it's still getting there
in terms of adding watermarks and so on
the flink team was enthusiastic about
how well the data flow model provided a
desirable way of modeling those data
processing pipelines how did
Flinx data processing work prior to its
implementation of the beam model you
know that's a great question and one I
have the background dancer oh okay fair
enough
do you have much knowledge on how they
went about making their processing
system beam compliant I mean I think you
know they we definitely had some early
chats with them when the paper got out
and then we ended up having some you
know some hangouts to chat with them and
talk about these concepts and the thing
I loved is that some guys are wicked
smart right they crack this stuff deeply
so we're really able to have these deep
technical conversations with them which
was a lot of fun to see how they take
they ended up you know evolving in a
similar direction then we were able to
refine the two and really get them to
align so can you tell me what is
involved in making a system beam
compliant like you know for example what
does Apache what do both Apache flank
and Apache spark have to implement in
order to make their api's beam compliant
so I think you know the the core
concepts in beam are things like
element-wise processing right that's
that's very standard since the MapReduce
days most people most systems can do
that that very easily then we've got you
know the different styles of aggregation
and windowing and this is where systems
start to diverge a little bit in their
ability to support the beam model and
and some some will be able to do that
and some won't as much so we've laid out
on the Bema site a really nice matrix of
sort of all the concepts and what the
current status is of support for each of
these different runners
let's talk about that term more what is
a beam pipeline runner yeah so that's
you right your beam pipeline and we
really again want that to be only about
the shape of your data and your
algorithms and your business logic then
the beam runner is the thing that takes
that and actually executes sit for you
now most beam runners they want to
actually do this at scale and there so
what they do is they shell out to an
existing system so most runners will
take that generalize beam pipeline and
translate it into the primitives used by
a system like spark or flink and call
out to that system for you would you
have one runner that actually does the
implementation that's called the direct
runner and that's just your simple sort
of in-memory runner so that one is is
use great it's great for testing unit
tests and integration and integration
tests and development and so on but most
of the runners that actually do this at
scale are really wrappers around other
distributed processing environments so
when I'm defining my beam pipeline what
does that look like is there like a file
format or a configuration style that I
use that will work across all of the
different beam pipeline runners that
have been implemented so there's two
answer that I'd like to do the short
term in the long term right so in the
short term what you do to write a beam
pipeline is use the Java SDK which
generates you know lets you say things
like I'm gonna create a pipeline I'm
gonna read from this type of data I'm
going to count it I'm going to join it
I'm gonna window it like this so I'm
gonna write it over there basically what
you're doing is writing a Java program
that builds a dag that describes the
shape of your pipeline and then from
that that the representation of that dag
is what is then translated into each of
the systems so that's where we're at
right now where we're mainly Java based
but our goal is to really support as
many languages as you want alright we've
just actually gotten started on the
Python SDK it's now in a feature branch
on beam but because when we use the term
beam programming model we want to use
that instead of SDK because the concepts
in beam are much more general right it's
just which language you use to express
those
that's just almost just an
implementation detail so where we'd like
to get to is the part where we have a
language independent representation of a
beam pipeline which means we can have
beam sdks in multiple languages that
will go ahead and generate that graph
description that describes the pipeline
and the data shapes and then the runners
can pick that up and go ahead and run
them so that will make it very easy for
for users to choose the language that
works best for whatever else they're
doing and the runtime that works best so
there are plenty of companies that have
a streaming system that is already in
place at their company whether it's
flank or spark or storm is one of the
visions for Apache beam to be this way
to move forward with new streaming
systems while maintaining a back
compatibility with your old streaming
systems I think unfortunately it's a
little more complicated than that
because you have to in order to use beam
there's a step of rewriting your logic
into beam so if you have a Flint cluster
that you got up and running and you're
really comfortable with it you're
welcome to run beam on that Flint
cluster but it is gonna require some
effort on your part to front-load the
work to use beam right so it's it's not
as easy to transition from you know I've
got a bunch of business logic in one
system already and that's that's a real
shame I think that's part of you know
what makes this a hard project and what
we really want to get the community
involved and working to help folks
understand why this model is an
improvement over the previous ways that
people have expressed programs so what
are the discussions with the community
like and why is it important for beam to
be an Apache project well I've had she's
the Apache Software Foundation is where
all the Big Data stuff is right
everything's there Hadoop and spark data
formats like parquet and Avro and and
storm Cassandra so flink
plenty of things are there so it's
absolutely the right group of data
processing geeks for us to join in with
and I think you know what we're really
looking forward to is what happens when
try to generalize this model across all
these different systems right we built
the initial beginnings of the beam model
obviously came out of cloud dataflow so
it was very much tied to how cloud
dataflow chose to execute things but
when we generalize that and we see sort
of the diversity of the way these
different systems work it really helps
you to separate out what is properties
of your data and your algorithm from
what is properties of that specific
runtime so can can you help me
understand a little bit more I think I
right maybe kind of touched on this
question a little bit but what are the
pervasive strengths and weaknesses of
these different streaming systems like
once we have this unified programming
model that gives the top-level
description of how we are creating our
data pipelines how should we be
evaluating which systems to run that
data model on top of so I think there it
will come down to you know which
features of beam are really important
for your use case so I think as we've
already talked about some systems do a
better job of distinguishing event time
and processing time I think that it's
very clear that the the streaming
community as a whole is moving in that
direction and being able to distinguish
those two but some systems are slightly
further along than others in their
ability to do that
there's also dimensions like do you need
your processing to be at most once at
least once or exactly once so there are
systems that are able to work in real
time and get data out fast by
potentially you know duplicating
elements and double counting things or
potentially losing elements and for many
applications that's okay if you just
want rough you know rough heuristics
about your data that may be a trade-off
you're totally willing to make but other
systems are going to be able to provide
exactly once guarantees which you know
that might be what you want if you're
running a billing pipeline or something
where money's involved right so this
exactly once processing you could call
this strong consistency why is this form
of correctness often challenging and
streaming system
well you have to be able to hand off the
data and sort of handshake with the next
part of the system as the data goes
through the pipeline right you basically
you're reading in an element you're
you're processing it and you want to
make sure that you don't act back to
whoever you read it from until you have
persisted it somewhere right because
machines fail it happens all the time
things go offline that where connections
go down like what is how are you going
to make sure that failures don't cause
data loss that's really the trick so is
this like the equivalent of three phase
commit in a database transaction right
something like that and then as you as
you're tracking also you know reasoning
about these different time dimensions
and buffering things across windows and
and things that you know it's pretty
complicated to keep track of this across
different stages in the pipeline tell me
more about your work on cloud dataflow
cloud dataflow is the Google hosted
version of dataflow what is the cloud
dataflow project right so cloud dataflow
is a part of Google cloud platform and
it is exactly you know you can think of
it as we finished this transition
towards Apache beam as being a fully
managed service for executing beam
pipelines so in other words you describe
the shape of your data and then will
then deal with all the nastiness under
the hood you know will provision the
machines spin them up tear them down
scale the number of machines dynamically
as you're executing which is a huge deal
right you know in a batch pipeline you
often see that the amount of data that
you're processing changes throughout the
life of the pipeline you might start
with a huge amount of data that you're
filtering down to a very small amount of
data which then somehow expands to a
really large amount of data and so
through those different phases you might
want different numbers of machines you
don't want to be prevent
over-provisioning I'm paying for more
machines and you need or if you're under
provisioning then you're going slower
than you have to so being able to
dynamically adapt to that is a huge
benefit is that to say that the
streaming applications were writing
today we have to write a lot of
management like server management code
that is maybe not going to have to be
written on top of the future cloud
platforms yeah I think you know we we
really want to get into the the mode
where the system it's a no nobs
experience you don't have to tune the
amount of RAM you're using the number of
machines you're using how they're
configured right you want to be focusing
as an application developer as a data
processing person on your data and your
algorithms you don't want to be futzing
with the system that's that's running
that for you so what does building that
as an automated feature what does that
look like from your point of view well I
think it's a really interesting back and
forth between the programming model and
the service so if you think about what
makes these systems complicated is
you're not just sort of giving them a
couple instructions and letting them go
off and calculate something for you
you're giving them bits of your own
serialized code to execute so these
systems right they're handling sort of
getting the data from one place to
another and running this stage and then
that they're doing that management but
the code that's executing what you're
doing to every element how you're
aggregating all that's described by the
user which means when you implement a
system to do this the system is almost
dealing with all these little black
boxes that are your user code and so
it's taking data and giving it to your
user code and then taking it from that
giving it to something else and what it
doesn't know is how that user codes
going to behave so designing that makes
it very difficult to for example
paralyze if I don't know how long your
code is gonna run I don't know how many
machines to do it how to schedule it if
I have no visibility into what it's
going to do so designing an SDK in a
programming model that gives the system
just the right hooks to be able to
efficiently schedule and rebalance that
work is one of the the really fun parts
so in order for this project to be to
reach the fruition that you want it to
do each of the popular streaming systems
need to implement a beam compliant model
so I think you know beam is we want
enough to write I don't think everyone
needs to what we
really want to set up with Apache beam
is at the core of it it is just this
programming model the set of concepts
right and then we want to set up a
framework that allows someone who is a
language developer who has a passion for
Ruby or R or NGO or Visual Basic
whatever to come along and help build
out the SDK for that language in beam
right to let you build the umpires in
that language so that it feels native to
people who live and breathe that
language at the same time we want to
allow people who have a runtime
environment you know they have some sort
of distributed processing system to come
and teach teach beam how to run programs
on that environment so what that will
really do is let the community to decide
which paths are the most exciting I
think is being we see our our job to set
up this framework that allows these
different things to flourish and as to
what paths become the most most popular
and most well-loved and used that'll
depend on the user communities so one of
the increased expectations that we've
had about our data processing that we've
been discussing in this episode is the
idea that you need improved fidelity on
the difference between event time and
processing time what are the things that
you think we're going to be focusing
more on with regards to our data as time
goes on maybe geospatial data or I don't
know some other aspect of the shape of
our data what things do you think are
going to be changing the next five to
ten years well I think yet so a venn
time and processing time is a big one
and I think we're also really seeing you
know folks starting to understand that
that's streaming is there is a runtime
choice right what you're do you want to
separate out those data shapes from
where you execute them and how you
execute them and by giving people that
layer of portability it will make things
much better in the future for the way
you write your programs without having
to leak those underlying implementation
details up into your user code okay so
how can people get started with dataflow
or with Google's cloud
version of dataflow so if you want to
come and run on Google cloud platform
right now you know just come check us
out at cloud.google.com we've got
getting started free trials you can come
you can try out dataflow you can use
that so you know if that's what you're
interested in that is absolutely great
come do that I think also I want to put
out a call to action for Apache beam
right beam Bhima is a community that is
much more broad than Google we've got
folks from from multiple companies
Google included but also you know data
artisans and cloud era and PayPal and
Talend
Intel folks working on making that
programming model really the most
generalized efficient unified model that
we can build and so there we're really
trying to kick-start that development
community so you know you can come to be
minkyu better at Apache org and you know
join the dev list start listening to the
discussions read our contribution guide
grab a starter task like really dive in
and start helping contribute to that
community great and where can people
find out more about you and your work oh
I guess I'm on Twitter Francis J Perry
that's probably the main place I guess I
read the read the cloud data or the data
flow model paper from vldb last year yes
that's an illuminating paper and also I
would say some of the videos on YouTube
about data flow and event time
processing yep versus yeah there's
there's basically there's some videos
and also there's a series of blog posts
actually written by a co-worker of mine
Tyler a cadeau if you search for
O'Reilly the world beyond batch
streaming one 101 and streaming 102 he
goes through a lot of these concepts and
he's got these magic animating gifts
that really show you sort of examples of
watermarks progressing through event
time and processing time and those magic
animating gifts are really the best way
to understand this it's so hard to
describe in words but wouldn't you see
it starts to make a lot more sense right
but you know as I was preparing for this
show that was one of the things I was
struggling with is how to articulate
this discussion of the watermarks and
the event time versus processing time
and I do think that probably the visual
representations are
the best places to look so we'll we'll
put that those in the show notes what in
real quick was there anything that
particularly from those the streaming
101 and streaming 102 presentations that
Tyler put together was there anything
about streaming that we didn't cover
that you'd like to touch on you know I
think we hit the major points right we
that we wanted you start thinking about
data shape and bounded and unbounded
separate from implementation details and
that by tuning these different axes of
event time and processing time we can we
can really cover stuff I think another
thing we can't we didn't really we
weren't able to show visually right now
is the code that you write in the beam
model is so beautifully modular right
the questions the what where when and
how they're literally line after you
know four lines in a row and it makes it
so easy to build these modular pipelines
where you can tune each of those
independently so if you go and look look
online there's a blog post comparing
sort of the the dataflow beam SDK to
what it looks like to write similar
programs and SPARC for example and you
can really see that these concepts
become much more reusable and much more
modular and you don't have to sort of
leak the implementation details into
your user code that's great okay well
Francis thanks a lot for coming on the
show I really enjoyed this conversation
excellent thanks for chatting ok great
getting software to your users quickly
and reliably is the most important part
of being a software engineer snap
sea-ice cloud-based continuous
integration and continuous deployment
tool lets you set up in minutes with
your github account and within a few
clicks we'll have your first pipeline
running discover and fix your bugs
quickly before pushing the production by
setting up stages from simple ones to
complex that run automatically when you
push your changes need more speed run
tests in parallel with expanded workers
and get your feedback fast deploy to
Heroku AWS and more we even integrate
with slack to give you updates on your
builds go to snap dot CI slash software
radio and build test and deploy free for
30 days snap CI embodies the lessons
that thought Works has learned from 20
years of software deployment the same
lessons that have been written about by
Martin Fowler and J's humble check it
out at snap CI slash software radio
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio gang to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Applause]
[Music]
you